<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>p-values on Median Watch</title>
    <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/tags/p-values/</link>
    <description>Recent content in p-values on Median Watch</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://medianwatch.netlify.com/tags/p-values/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A year without p-values</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_year/</guid>
      <description>My values are not p-valuesOne year ago after another stupid fight with a journal about p-values, I made a pledge to go without them for a year. Here’s how it went.
But first, why?I am aware of the arguments for and against p-values. I have used p-values for a long while and they can be a useful statistic.
The reason I ditched them is because almost nobody in health and medical research interprets them correctly, wrongly thinking they reveal the probability that the null hypothesis is true (other misinterpretations are available).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear p-values, it&#39;s not me, it&#39;s not you, it&#39;s everyone else</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_pledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_pledge/</guid>
      <description>Yet another p-value run-in.For a recent observational study I tried to limit the use of p-values in the paper.My colleagues wanted more p-values and I had to politely push back.During one team meeting I even offered to put the p-values in if someone could accurately tell me what they meant … silence.
Predicting that the reviewers would also want to see more p-values, I added this sentence to the paper’s methods: “We have tried to limit the use of p-values, as they are often misunderstood or misinterpreted, and elected to discuss clinically meaningful differences.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
