<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Median Watch</title>
    <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Median Watch</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Reflections on experiencing a natural disaster</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/disaster/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 03 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/disaster/</guid>
      <description>Sometimes I fantasise about being in an earthquake. Not a big one, just a little one. Enough to feel the ground shake, to see the earth move for a few seconds.
I should be careful what I wish for. Last Sunday I was in the plughole of a proper natural disaster as massive amounts of rain tried to barge its way into our house. It wasn’t any fun. Our house is fine, and other friends have had far worse experiences, but it has knocked me about a bit, and it’s been hard to focus on work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>University league tables cost money and cause harm</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/league_tables/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 19 Nov 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/league_tables/</guid>
      <description>Re-posted from Campus Morning Mail with permission.
Last week I pledged to work for any Australian university for free if they abandoned league tables. So far no university has been bold enough to take up my offer.
I am one of many academics who have criticised league tables using science, demonstrating their many statistical flaws and negative consequences. But all this scientific criticism has had no impact. Instead, the number of league tables is growing and so is their influence.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Funding schemes that cost as much as they reward</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/hidden_funding_costs/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 16 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/hidden_funding_costs/</guid>
      <description>Johnson &amp;amp; Johnson have a funding scheme for women in STEM. Of course this is a great idea and much needed given the chronic under-representation of women in health and medical research, which was confirmed again this week with the latest NHMRC figures.
But there’s a huge potential problem with this scheme: the success rate is under 1%. The last round had 650 applications and 6 awarded. Given this incredibly low success rate, this scheme could be costing as much as it rewards.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A year without p-values</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_year/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 10 Sep 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_year/</guid>
      <description>One year ago after another stupid fight with a journal about p-values, I made a pledge to go without them for a year. Here’s how it went.
But first, why?I am aware of the arguments for and against p-values. I have used p-values for a long while and they can be a useful statistic.
The reason I ditched them is because almost nobody in health and medical research interprets them correctly, wrongly thinking they reveal the probability that the null hypothesis is true (other misinterpretations are available).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding racist users in an online football game</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/racism_football/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 11 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/racism_football/</guid>
      <description>In 1998, the French men’s team won the football World Cup for the first time in their history. For most of the country, even non-football fans, it was a joyous moment and the trigger for a massive national party, especially as the tournament was in France with the final in Paris.
At least one Frenchman did not join the party: the rancorous politician Jean Marie Le Pen, who complained that the team was not “French enough,” a cowardly reference to the number of black players in the team.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>An apology to the public</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/an_apology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/an_apology/</guid>
      <description>Sorry state.A few years ago I thought about writing an article that apologised to the public about the poor state of health and medical research. Their tax pays for this research and they give their time and data, and yet far too often the final results are totally unreliable.
In the end I bottled it; too worried about the potential harm to my career. But today I’ve read this important paper from a group of statistical colleagues and it’s given me the nerve to apologise.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Most citations are rubbish</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/rubbish_citations/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 06 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/rubbish_citations/</guid>
      <description>Blog pauseIt’s been a long while between blogs. I won’t bore you with how busy I’ve been, but one thing that’s kept me away from the fun of writing blogs is the “fun” of writing grants.
BeansTo get more research funding we rightly have to explain the impact of our past funding.It’s possible to get examples of impact by seeing how other researchers have cited your work.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I humbly present the novel c-index</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/c_index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/c_index/</guid>
      <description>Show me the shortcutScientists are busy people. Busy people love a short-cut because it gives them more time to be busy.
The p-value is a well-used scientific short-cut. It can decide for us whether something is important or not, and it’s based on an equation so it must be right.
Another heaven-sent shortcut is the h-index which allows us to decide the careers of researchers based on just one number (also made by an equation).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A change to judging career disruption</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/career_disruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/career_disruption/</guid>
      <description>Re-posted from this 2016 AusHSI blog because this is still an issue.
Let’s start with the obvious. Winning funding for health and medical research is soul-crushingly hard. Success rates for major schemes are under 20%, so failure is the norm.
Your application will be judged by a panel of 6 to 12 senior researchers. A key marker of success is your track record, which may simply mean the number and quality of your papers, and your previous research funding (a very circular measure).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Dear p-values, it&#39;s not me, it&#39;s not you, it&#39;s everyone else</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_pledge/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/pvalue_pledge/</guid>
      <description>Yet another p-value run-in.For a recent observational study I tried to limit the use of p-values in the paper.My colleagues wanted more p-values and I had to politely push back.During one team meeting I even offered to put the p-values in if someone could accurately tell me what they meant … silence.
Predicting that the reviewers would also want to see more p-values, I added this sentence to the paper’s methods: “We have tried to limit the use of p-values, as they are often misunderstood or misinterpreted, and elected to discuss clinically meaningful differences.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Not waving but drowning in data</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/not-waving/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 03 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/not-waving/</guid>
      <description>Our paper examining trends in acronyms in abstracts was recently published in eLife.We examined over 26 million abstracts from the PubMed database, which is easily the largest data set I’ve ever used.In this post I talk about some of the challenges and benefits of dealing with such a massive data set.
Data greedOne of the most common mistakes I see researchers — new and experienced — make is to collect too much data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Goodbye to all that</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/goodbye-president/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 23 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/goodbye-president/</guid>
      <description>Today I end my two year stint as president of the Statistical Society of Australia. As I press “submit” on my presidency, here’s a hodge-podge of reflections.
I was delighted to be president, and I will miss being able to say, “I’m the president of the Stats Society”. Statistics has given me an incredible career and I feel I owe something back.
It might sound strange to feel a debt to a thing, but statistics is a big thing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>When should I quit research? An evidence-based approach</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/quit-research/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 17 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/quit-research/</guid>
      <description>Re-posted from the AusHSI blog (8 May 2015).
After yet another failed fellowship application I considered if I should leave research. I now have seven fellowship failures and no successes, and that seems like a lot.
Success rates for grants are nose-diving and even the former head of the NHMRC says that researchers should be considering other careers (pay-walled). I’ve spent a lot of time running research projects for no money, but working for no money is a luxury I can’t afford.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I did the dishes.</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/did-the-dishes/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 08 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/did-the-dishes/</guid>
      <description>My daughter loves a song by Parry Gripp called “I did the dishes”. The chorus is “I did the dishes, I’m a hero.”
I can’t work out if the song is trying to encourage kids to do the dishes, or if it’s making fun of people who think their housework is heroic, or a bit of both.
“Plates, done! Bowls, done! Gravy boat, done!”
I helped some people, I’m a heroHere’s a screenshot of some my colleagues who I’ve helped with their statistics.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Working Weekends and Late Nights</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/working-weekends-and-late-nights/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 20 May 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/working-weekends-and-late-nights/</guid>
      <description>Re-posted from the March 2020 issue of Advocate.
The smell of pool chlorine reminds us of work. Both of us admit to doing emails while sitting at the local pool waiting for the kids to finish their lessons, as well as at cafés, on airplanes, waiting in queues. At least one of us does the odd email or two from the bathroom. We are academics and therefore work anywhere, anytime (maybe most of the time?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>The COVID-19 crisis is amplifying shortcomings in health and medical research.</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/research-waste-covid/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 29 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/research-waste-covid/</guid>
      <description>Re-posted from Campus Morning Mail.
Poor quality medical research is nothing new. A major cause is the race to be published first, which means researchers do not adequately check their work.
The COVID-19 crisis has put an already pressured system under even more strain, and the cracks are clearly visible.
Small studies have been used to justify massive changes in clinical practice, such as the early results on Hydroxychloroquine, which have looked less promising as more work is published.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Playing the scientific record backwards.</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/climate-crisis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 15 Apr 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/climate-crisis/</guid>
      <description>I’ve done a lot of research on seasonal models. I’ve always enjoyed playing with the elegantly simple sinusoid function, which can fit a remarkable array of shapes with just a few parameters. Put enough sinusoids together and you can create any sound. When Fourier discovered this, it was considered too simple to be true.
A great number of diseases are seasonal, so these models are useful as well as being mathematically pleasing.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>It&#39;s fun to look at the Y A C M (Yet Another COVID Model)</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/covid-uncertainty/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 31 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/covid-uncertainty/</guid>
      <description>Yet another COVID model.I did this modelling because I was asked to provide some COVID estimates for a hospital. There have been lots of models in the last few weeks and I don’t want to reduce the signal-to-noise ratio in this vitally important area, but I’m sharing this in case someone finds my approach useful. All the code is here. I have used similar models before to simulate disease numbers over time, for example my PhD student Dimity used microsimulation to examine the long-term effects of climate change (Stephen and Barnett 2017).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Mistakes, I’ve made a few, but then again, not too few to mention</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/making-mistakes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 17 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/making-mistakes/</guid>
      <description>Statistics can be hardHere’s a great quote about working with statistics from the fantastic statistician David Spiegelhalter: “I am often asked why people tend to find probability a difficult and unintuitive idea, and I reply that, after forty years researching and teaching in this area, I have finally concluded that it is because probability really is a difficult and unintuitive idea” (Spiegelhalter 2019).
Someone who attended my one-day statistics refresher course expressed disappointment in their evaluation that after a day’s training they did not now feel like an expert.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A 2-for-1 deal for female researchers</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/funding-gender-disparity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/funding-gender-disparity/</guid>
      <description>The gender disparity in research funding.There is a large gender disparity in the number of research grants awarded in Australia. For years men have won more funding than women. This disparity in success is driven by a disparity in applications, as women apply far less often. Success rates for men and women are relatively close, so policies to reduce the gender disparity in funding should focus on encouraging more applications from women.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Why start blogging now?</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/2020-02-28-first-post/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 28 Feb 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/2020-02-28-first-post/</guid>
      <description>The title for this blog is a homage the ABC TV show &amp;ldquo;Media Watch&amp;rdquo; which critiques the Australian media and is never short of content. Similarly there&amp;rsquo;s a lot wrong in the way people use statistics, so this blog is mainly about the use and misuse of statistics.
I&amp;rsquo;ve got a post coming on how my research has been misused by those trying to deny the climate crisis. I also want to write about some statistical mistakes I&amp;rsquo;ve made in published papers, which I realise may just help the climate change propagandists to undermine my credibility.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
