<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>career on Median Watch</title>
    <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/tags/career/</link>
    <description>Recent content in career on Median Watch</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-uk</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://medianwatch.netlify.com/tags/career/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>An apology to the public</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/an_apology/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Jun 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/an_apology/</guid>
      <description>Sorry stateA few years ago I thought about writing an article that apologised to the public about the poor state of health and medical research. The public pay for this research and give their time and data, and yet often the results provided by research are totally unreliable.
In the end I bottled it; too worried about the harm to my career. But today I’ve read this important paper from a group of statistical colleagues and it’s given me the nerve to speak up.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>I humbly present the novel c-index</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/c_index/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 23 Nov 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/c_index/</guid>
      <description>Show me the shortcutScientists are busy people. Busy people love a short-cut because it gives them more time to be busy.
The p-value is a well-used scientific short-cut. It can decide for us whether something is important or not, and it’s based on an equation so it must be right.
Another heaven-sent shortcut is the h-index which allows us to decide the careers of researchers based on just one number (also made by an equation).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A change to judging career disruption</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/career_disruption/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/career_disruption/</guid>
      <description>Re-posted from this 2016 AusHSI blog because this is still an issue.
Let’s start with the obvious. Winning funding for health and medical research is soul-crushingly hard. Success rates for major schemes are under 20%, so failure is the norm.
Your application will be judged by a panel of 6 to 12 senior researchers. A key marker of success is your track record, which may simply mean the number and quality of your papers, and your previous research funding (a very circular measure).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A 2-for-1 deal for female researchers</title>
      <link>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/funding-gender-disparity/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 02 Mar 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://medianwatch.netlify.com/post/funding-gender-disparity/</guid>
      <description>The gender disparity in research funding.There is a large gender disparity in the number of research grants awarded in Australia. For years men have won more funding than women. This disparity in success is driven by a disparity in applications, as women apply far less often. Success rates for men and women are relatively close, so policies to reduce the gender disparity in funding should focus on encouraging more applications from women.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
